<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-05T22:28:33+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Topic modelling learning journal (part 2)</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2026/topic-modelling-II/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Topic modelling learning journal (part 2)"/><published>2026-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2026/topic-modelling-II</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2026/topic-modelling-II/"><![CDATA[<p>In my previous post, <a href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2026/topic-modelling-I/">Topic modelling learning journal (part 1)</a>, I shared how I approached learning topic modelling as a beginner. For me, the fastest way to learn is always through a concrete project, so I chose <strong>ARC Discovery Projects from the 2023–2026 funding rounds</strong> as my first formal NLP task.</p> <p>Like many researchers who have spent a large part of their academic life chasing funding, I believe that understanding <strong>emerging trends</strong>—and what kinds of topics attract funding—is extremely important.</p> <p>The dataset consists of <strong>1,961 project summaries across four years</strong>, and the goal is to cluster them into topics based on their text descriptions.</p> <p>This turned out to be more challenging than I initially expected: the summaries are relatively short, the language is highly domain-specific, and many concepts are expressed implicitly rather than explicitly.</p> <p>All of these factors make it harder for classical topic models to identify clean, well-separated themes. Still, I decided to stick with this dataset and see how far I could push the approach.</p> <p>I ended up with two findings that I found particularly interesting. In this second post of the topic modelling learning journal series, I focus on providing a high-level overview of the research space represented in this dataset. In the final post, I will dive deeper into the topics themselves and what they reveal.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="analysis-pipeline-overview"><strong>Analysis pipeline overview</strong></h3> <p>There are many sophisticated NLP libraries available—such as gensim and nltk—and I did experiment with them. However, for this project, I found that using my own scripts combined with scikit-learn was both efficient and flexible enough.</p> <p>The Jupyter notebook used for this analysis is available <a href="">here</a>.</p> <p>I started with preprocessing the project summaries using a minimal setup:</p> <ul> <li>text normalisation (lowercasing, removing punctuation, stripping numbers)</li> <li>lemmatization (e.g. projects → project)</li> <li>stopword removal (generic stopwords such as and, the)</li> </ul> <p>I then converted the text into numerical vectors representing word importance using:</p> <ul> <li>Bag-of-Words, which simply counts word occurrences</li> <li>TF-IDF, which adjusts word counts to reduce the influence of very common terms</li> </ul> <p>Because I was interested in the structure of the project space at this stage, I first applied a dimensionality reduction technique to project the high-dimensional TF-IDF representations onto a 2D surface based on shared vocabulary patterns.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="visualizing-the-project-content-space"><strong>Visualizing the project content space</strong></h3> <p>The interactive figure below shows the projection of all 1,961 projects onto a 2D surface, which I refer to as the project content space. Each point represents a project and is colour-coded by its Field of Research (FOR) code.</p> <p>You can navigate this space by toggling individual FOR codes on or off, and by hovering over points to view project descriptions.</p> <iframe src="/assets/img/blog_figure/topic-modeling-pca-FOR.html" width="100%" height="500" frameborder="0"></iframe> <p>When I first saw this figure, it was genuinely exciting. Projects sharing the same FOR code tend to cluster closely together, which suggests that the model is successfully capturing meaningful similarities based purely on text. In other words, it “understands” that projects discussing similar topics use similar language.</p> <p>This result shouldn’t be surprising—but it is still fascinating to see how much structure can be recovered using nothing more than free, open-source tools running on a personal computer.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="broad-structure-of-the-research-space"><strong>Broad structure of the research space</strong></h3> <p>The projection forms a rough triangular shape, suggesting the presence of three broad extremes in the research landscape.</p> <p>The right corner is dominated by biology-related fields, top-left corner by chemical sciences, and the bottom-left corner by social sciences. This makes intuitive sense: these disciplines use very different vocabularies and conceptual frameworks.</p> <p>What <em>surprised</em> me slightly is how elongated the triangle is toward the biology corner. This suggests that biology-related research may be more linguistically distinct from both chemical sciences and social sciences than those two are from each other—at least in this dataset.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="zooming-in-the-biology-corner"><strong>Zooming in: the biology corner</strong></h3> <p>The biology corner is mainly dominated by <em>31: Biological Sciences</em> and <em>32: Biomedical and Clinical Sciences</em>. These two fields largely overlap and span from the right corner of the triangle (representing more niche or specialised biology research) toward the centre (which corresponds to more interdisciplinary projects).</p> <p>To make this more concrete, consider two projects both classified under <em>31: Biological Sciences</em> but located far apart in the projection. One project (full description <a href="https://rms.arc.gov.au/RMS/Report/Download/Report/1b0c8b2e-7bb0-4f2d-8f52-ad207cfbb41d/273#:~:text=Parry-,This%20project%20aims%20to,environmental%20benefits%20to%20Australia.,-The">here</a>) focuses on discovering how nature produces vivid colours using nanostructures—language that places it closer to the chemical sciences. Another project (full description <a href="https://rms.arc.gov.au/RMS/Report/Download/Report/1b0c8b2e-7bb0-4f2d-8f52-ad207cfbb41d/243#:~:text=Cardillo-,This%20project%20aims%20to,investment%20in%20biodiversity%20databases.,-The">here</a>) focuses on biodiversity data and investment, which pulls it toward the social sciences.</p> <p>Reading the project descriptions makes this separation immediately intuitive, and seeing it emerge automatically from text alone was one of the most satisfying moments of this project.</p> <hr/> <p>In the next and final post of this series, I’ll move beyond the geometric structure of the project space and focus on explicit topic modelling—the topics themselves and the trends that emerge across ARC Discovery Projects.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[explore the research space of ARC discovery projects]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Topic modelling learning journal (part 1)</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2026/topic-modelling-I/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Topic modelling learning journal (part 1)"/><published>2026-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2026/topic-modelling-I</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2026/topic-modelling-I/"><![CDATA[<p>I come from a machine learning background, mostly in the context of data science. Recently, however, I’ve become increasingly interested in <strong>natural language processing (NLP)</strong>.</p> <p>During my PhD, I constantly heard about NLP and large language models (LLMs). Everyone was using ChatGPT and amazed by how good it is. At the same time, there was an explosion of research papers on arXiv across computer science, materials science, and beyond, with some papers suggesting that models like GPT could help discover new materials with better properties. When I started job hunting, many roles explicitly required experience with NLP or LLMs. Looking back now, I fully understand why.</p> <p>At the time, though, I was sceptical. I felt that NLP and LLMs were surrounded by hype, and I couldn’t see an immediate or practical use for them in my own research workflow. I tended to associate NLP almost exclusively with <strong>text generation</strong>, which wasn’t something I thought I needed.</p> <p>That perspective has changed.</p> <p>In this three-part series, I want to share my learning journey into <strong>NLP</strong> as a beginner. In this first post, I focus on what motivated me to explore NLP more seriously and how I built a clearer mental model of the field over the past three months. In the next two parts, I will share the results of my first NLP project: topic modelling of ARC Discovery Projects.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="why-i-became-interested-in-nlp"><strong>Why I became interested in NLP</strong></h3> <p>Very recently, I realised something that now feels obvious in hindsight:</p> <blockquote> <p>Language and text are also forms of data, and increasingly, they are the main form of data I interact with.</p> </blockquote> <p>Job descriptions, research proposals, funding schemes, academic papers across disciplines, and descriptions of research areas I might want to move into—almost everything I needed to process was text. Reading, filtering, and synthesising all of this information took a huge amount of time.</p> <p>I started asking myself:</p> <blockquote> <p>There must be tools that could help me process and understand large collections of text more efficiently.</p> </blockquote> <p>This was when I began to seriously think about <strong>treating text as data</strong>. At first, I didn’t even know this fell under NLP. I simply searched for Python packages that could process text in a structured, data-driven way. To my surprise (and delight), I discovered that this is exactly what NLP is about.</p> <p>Over time, I also realised that <strong>LLMs are only one branch of NLP</strong>, albeit the most visible one. Training or fine-tuning something like ChatGPT may feel out of reach, but NLP as a field is much broader and far more accessible. A word cloud is a very simple NLP technique. LinkedIn job recommendations rely heavily on NLP. There are many flavours of NLP beyond text generation.</p> <p>For me, the most relevant part of NLP is about <strong>understanding, organising, and extracting structure from text</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="the-learning-journey"><strong>The learning journey</strong></h3> <p>Over the past few months, I’ve been actively job hunting. The roles I encountered on job boards often felt loosely defined, spanning an almost unlimited range of possibilities. As I applied for more positions, I started wondering: <em>What exactly is the job space I’m exploring? Are there hidden structures or dominant themes?</em></p> <p>If you’re familiar with unsupervised learning, this idea is similar to <strong>dimensionality reduction</strong>—compressing high-dimensional data into two dimensions that can be visualised. Conceptually, topic modelling felt very familiar to me from a machine learning perspective. The main difference lies in <strong>how text is transformed into numerical features</strong>.</p> <p>There is no shortage of information online. ChatGPT can generate plenty of code snippets and explanations, and I used it extensively. I asked ChatGPT to generate code for transforming job descriptions into numerical representations that could be fed into machine learning models. The results were quite good, and I shared some of this in my <a href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/job-hunting/">previous blog post</a>.</p> <p>However, like acquiring any new skill in the era of chatbots, the information I encountered was <strong>fragmented</strong>. I didn’t always understand <em>why</em> things worked, what the results really meant, or how different methods fit together within the broader NLP landscape.</p> <p>I decided to slow down and explore this field more seriously during the Christmas holiday. Gradually, I learned that what I was doing fell under <strong>topic modelling</strong>, a subfield of NLP that aims to automatically discover structure in large collections of documents.</p> <p>The promise was compelling. <strong>Imagine being able to quickly group thousands of research papers into themes and get a high-level sense of emerging or “hot” topics in a field.</strong> That alone could save an enormous amount of time.</p> <p>To build a more systematic understanding—something that could bridge what I already knew about machine learning with this new NLP domain—I turned to a few very useful textbooks:</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>The Handbook of NLP with Gensim</strong> by Chris Kuo</p> <p>By far the most helpful resource for me. It explains both the core concepts and implementation details, with just enough mathematics to understand what’s happening under the hood. The tone is technical but approachable, and surprisingly fun to read.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Hands-On Large Language Models</strong> by Jay Alammar &amp; Maarten grootendorst</p> <p>I generally like O’Reilly books for hands-on machine learning topics, and this one was no exception. Despite the title, the book starts from language models more broadly, both small and large. I didn’t read it cover to cover, but the introductory chapters gave me a strong high-level blueprint of NLP and how different language modelling approaches fit together.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Practical Natural Language Processing</strong> by Sowmya Vajjala et al.</p> <p>Another O’Reilly book, with a clear and structured explanation of NLP. I found it particularly helpful for understanding how different authors and practitioners approach NLP as a whole, and where topic modelling sits within that broader landscape.</p> </li> </ul> <hr/> <h3 id="my-beginners-understanding-of-topic-modelling"><strong>My beginner’s understanding of topic modelling</strong></h3> <p>After reading books, papers, blog posts, and experimenting extensively (with a lot of help from ChatGPT), I now have a <strong>preliminary but coherent mental model</strong> of topic modelling.</p> <p>Broadly, there are two families of approaches:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Classical methods</strong>, such as <em>Latent Semantic Analysis (LSA)</em> and <em>Latent Dirichlet Allocation (LDA)</em></li> <li><strong>Modern methods</strong>, such as <em>BERTopic</em>, which rely on transformer-based embeddings</li> </ul> <p>To me, this distinction feels very similar to <strong>machine learning vs. deep learning</strong>.</p> <p>Classical topic models are more interpretable, require fewer computational resources, but may sacrifice some flexibility or performance.</p> <p>Embedding-based methods often produce cleaner-looking topics, handle short or noisy text better, but are less interpretable and more computationally expensive.</p> <p>For my learning goals, I’m currently leaning towards <strong>classical approaches</strong>, especially LDA. Even though these models have been around for many years, they provide a strong conceptual foundation. I see them as essential baselines to understand before moving on to more complex models.</p> <hr/> <p>I hope this post provides enough background on my motivation for learning topic modelling and my current understanding of the field. In the next two parts, I’ll share how I applied what I learned in practice by modelling topics in ARC Discovery Projects based on their descriptions.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[to the wonderland of natural language processing]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding my employability after the PhD</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/job-hunting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding my employability after the PhD"/><published>2025-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/job-hunting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/job-hunting/"><![CDATA[<p>When I first heard the word employability, I thought it simply meant getting a job. But after finishing my PhD and stepping into the job-hunting world, I realised it’s something far more complex and personal.</p> <p>In today’s blog, I’d like to share my ongoing journey of understanding my own employability. I haven’t secured a job yet, so this post might sound a little uncertain or even negative at times. But that’s exactly where I am, figuring things out in real time.</p> <h3 id="from-a-clear-path-to-an-open-sea">From a clear path to an open sea</h3> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/job-hunting-0-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/job-hunting-0-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/job-hunting-0-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/job-hunting-0.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>One night, my husband and I were talking about how our career landscape have changed. Before the PhD, the path ahead felt like a road on solid ground: clear, predictable, and paved with milestones: bachelor’s, master’s, PhD.</p> <p>But once I reached the end of that road, it was as if the ground disappeared beneath my feet.</p> <p>Now, I find myself sailing on an open sea with no marked routes, but only possibilities stretching endlessly in all directions. The world suddenly seemed full of options—postdocs, industries, government jobs, yet I didn’t know where to go or even how to start navigating.</p> <h3 id="what-is-employability">What is employability?</h3> <p>At first, I thought “employability” was just another buzzword universities use. But during the recent Employability Symposium attended at UNSW I had a lightbulb moment: this is the word I’ve been looking for all along.</p> <p>According to Wikipedia, employability refers to the attributes of a person that make them able to gain and maintain employment,</p> <p>A line from the symposium stuck with me even more: “To be employed is to be at risk; to be employable is to be secure.”</p> <p>That’s when I realised employability isn’t about finding a job, but about understanding who I am, and the unique value I can bring to society.</p> <p>Ironically, this has been the most time-consuming and confusing part of my job-hunting journey — not sending out applications, not preparing for interviews, but trying to understand <em>myself</em>.</p> <h3 id="the-four-parts-of-employability">The four parts of Employability</h3> <p>One framework that helped me think about this is the Japanese concept of <strong>Ikigai</strong> — the intersection of:</p> <ul> <li>what you love,</li> <li>what you’re good at, and</li> <li>what the world needs.</li> <li>and what you can be paid for</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/ikigai-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/ikigai-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/ikigai-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/ikigai.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Towards the end of my PhD, I was overly optimistic and driven by curiosity. I loved the idea of <em>AI for biology and medicine</em> and thought it was exactly what the world needed. But when I started reading job ads, I realised I didn’t yet have the required skills— In fact, I couldn’t even understand many of the keywords.</p> <p>I was missing one key piece of the puzzle — <em>what I’m good at</em>.</p> <p>That discovery was humbling but necessary.</p> <h3 id="the-long-process-of-translating-myself">The Long process of translating myself</h3> <p>In the past few months, I’ve rewritten my CV coutless times, and each version represents a different version of myself tailored to the job description: data scientist, quantitative researcher, postdoc.</p> <p>Job hunting has forced me to translate my academic experience into the language of industry. Every job ad became a mirror showing me what I had and what I lacked.</p> <p>There were so many moments like:</p> <ul> <li>“Oh! I didn’t know I already have that skill!”</li> <li>and also, “I really wish I had learned that during my PhD…”</li> </ul> <p>If I could go back, I would start learning to articulate my employability <em>during</em> my PhD — not just assume that a degree alone would naturally lead to a job.</p> <h3 id="turning-frustration-into-visualisation">Turning Frustration into Visualisation</h3> <p>Well, as someone who loves data and visualisation, I couldn’t resist asking: <em>what does all this job-hunting data actually look like?</em></p> <p>How could I end this blog without a visualisation?</p> <p>This was my first attempt at analysing text-based data — I used job descriptions as the input, extracted keywords, and projected them using PCA to map the <em>landscape</em> of positions I’ve applied for. Each point represents one job; together, they form a visual summary of my search so far.</p> <iframe src="/assets/img/blog_figure/job-hunting-1.html" width="100%" height="500" frameborder="0"></iframe> <p>As you might guess, most of the applications end up with rejection. Reality is painful, but honestly, playing with these data was fun.</p> <p>At first, I felt deeply frustrated, convinced my employability must be terrible because of the rejections. But when I looked at the actual numbers, I realised I had only sent out <strong>ten applications</strong> in total. Statistically speaking, I’m still in the <em>very early stage</em> of job hunting.</p> <p>So — fingers crossed for the best!</p> <h3 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h3> <p>If you’re also in the middle of job hunting, I want to say this: I wouldn’t have known how challenging it is to find a job in Australia right now if I hadn’t gone through it myself.</p> <p>But I’ve also realised this process is more than just career exploration — it’s a journey of <em>self-awareness</em>.</p> <p>So take care of yourself. Be patient. Keep learning. It’s hard, but you’re not alone.</p> <p>Hang in there — and hopefully, we’ll both see the light at the end of the tunnel soon.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[where do I fit in?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DIY Perovskite crystal model - Origami, knitting and 3D printing</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/perovskite-diy-model/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DIY Perovskite crystal model - Origami, knitting and 3D printing"/><published>2025-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/perovskite-diy-model</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/perovskite-diy-model/"><![CDATA[<p>Most of my research happens inside a computer — simulating, visualizing, and analyzing atomic structures that exist only on a screen. But I’ve always loved handcrafts and making things in the real world. There’s something deeply satisfying about <em>holding</em> a model of the structure I usually see as colorful atoms on my monitor.</p> <p>During my PhD, I’ve been studying <strong>perovskites</strong> — a fascinating class of materials that appear everywhere from ceramics to solar cells. On the atomic scale, perovskites are built from repeating <strong>octahedra</strong> (eight-sided units) connected at their corners, forming a beautiful three-dimensional lattice.</p> <p>Over the years, I’ve explored several ways to <strong>bring this structure to life</strong> — blending science and creativity. In this post, I’ll share <strong>three hands-on ways</strong> to build your own perovskite crystal model:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Origami</strong> — fold your crystal lattice from paper</li> <li><strong>Knitting</strong> — create a soft, large-scale version</li> <li><strong>3D printing</strong> — design a durable, modular model for labs or demos</li> </ul> <p>Each method highlights a different aspect of the structure — geometry, scale, or modularity — and all are fun, tactile ways to explore materials science.</p> <h3 id="1-origami-perovskite"><strong>1. Origami Perovskite</strong></h3> <p>My first and simplest experiment was the origami perovskite. I made it in the very beginning of my perovskite journey while reading the classic paper <a href="https://doi.org/10.1107%2FS0567740872007976">“The Classification of Tilted Octahedra in Perovskites”</a> by Mike Glazer — a must-read for anyone studying crystal structures.</p> <p>I wanted a way to visualize how octahedral tilts affect symmetry in perovskites, so I decided to bring the structure to life with paper. All you need is some paper, thread, and a bit of time.</p> <p><strong>Difficulty:</strong> ★☆☆ (Beginner)</p> <p><strong>Materials:</strong> Paper, thread</p> <p>Start by cutting paper into roughly a 3:1 rectangular shape and folding origami octahedra. You can follow this excellent <a href="https://www.thesprucecrafts.com/origami-octahedron-instructions-2540641">step-by-step guide</a>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Once you’ve made a few octahedra, connect them at the corners using thread, gently tie them together to form a cubic network. I love this model because it’s flexible. You can tilt the octahedra to mimic the rotations that solid-state physicist observe in real perovskites.</p> <p>I used 30x10 cm rectangular paper, which makes the final model roughly <strong>50 million times larger</strong> than the atomic lattice!</p> <p>This is also a fantastic outreach activity. During the “Science in the Swamps” event with School of Chemistry at UNSW, we invited primary school kids and their families to fold their own octahedra. It was a bit tricky for smaller hands (and even some parents), but everyone loved seeing their creations come together into something scientific. In fact, I think the parents enjoyed it even more than the kids!</p> <p>Another great variation comes from this <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jaume-Roqueta/publication/266383933_Origami_of_petovskite_structure/links/542e966d0cf277d58e8ec28b/Origami-of-petovskite-structure.pdf">research-inspired project</a>. Their workflow is similar but they build each octahedron from six seperate square pieces. I’ll have to try this method next time!</p> <h3 id="2-knitted-perovskite"><strong>2. Knitted Perovskite</strong></h3> <p>The next method takes perovskite modeling to a softer level — <strong>knitting</strong>!</p> <p>This idea was inspired by a wonderful project called <a href="https://blogs.egu.eu/network/atomsi/2013/08/08/spinning-a-yarn-about-perovksite/"><strong>“The Perovskite Project”</strong></a> from the University of Surrey, where researchers and knitters collaborated to create a <strong>2-meter-high</strong> knitted perovskite, now proudly displayed in their Department of Chemistry.</p> <p>I also found two contributors who are experienced knitters and documented how they made it on their blogs: <a href="https://www.chemknits.com/2013/08/perovskite-crystal-project.html">ChemKnits</a> and <a href="https://ladynthread.blogspot.com/2013/07/the-perovskite-project.html">Lady N Thread</a>.</p> <p><strong>Difficulty:</strong> ★★☆ (Intermediate)</p> <p><strong>Materials:</strong> Yarn, knitting needles or crochet hooks, cardboard</p> <p>For my version, I used <strong>8-ply yarn</strong> to knit triangles (you can also crochet them). Then, I sewed eight triangles together to form an octahedron. Since the yarn shapes are too soft to hold on their own, I cut matching triangle pieces from cardboard, taped them together into an octahedron, and inserted them inside as supports.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/knitting-perovskite-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/knitting-perovskite-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/knitting-perovskite-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/knitting-perovskite.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>As you can tell, this project is still ongoing. It’s time-consuming but incredibly fun. So far, I’ve made 5 octahedra and plan to make 3 more and finish assembling them just in time for my graduation ceremony next month!</p> <h3 id="3-3d-printed-perovskite"><strong>3. 3D-Printed Perovskite</strong></h3> <p>The final version was my attempt to upgrade the origami perovskite model. I wanted something modular, where the octahedra could be assembled and disassembled quickly and freely — a hands-on kit for exploring different connectivity in perovskites.</p> <p>Thanks to my cousin <a href="https://zefangli.github.io">Zefang</a>, who’s pursuing a PhD in 3D printing (and also serves as my unofficial 3D-printing consultant) for helping me bring this idea to life during one of our brainstorming sessions.</p> <p><strong>Difficulty:</strong> ★★★ (Advanced)</p> <p><strong>Materials:</strong> 3D printer, small magnetic balls, superglue</p> <p>Each unit is 3D-printed as an octahedron with small cavities at each corner. (The .stl files are available here: [insert link].)</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-2.JPG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-2.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>When printing, orient one face flat on the bed for better stability. After printing, insert 5 mm <strong>magnetic balls</strong> into each corner cavity (based on the original 3D-print file size). Use superglue to secure them, aligning their poles along the axes.</p> <p>Be sure to alternate the poles — three corners with the north pole facing out and three with the south — so that the octahedra can connect without repelling each other.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Voilà! You now have a <strong>modular perovskite kit</strong> that can be arranged into 0D, 1D, 2D, or 3D perovskite structures. My office mates and I had great fun experimenting with different configurations during coffee breaks!</p> <h3 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h3> <p>Making these perovskite models has been one of the most enjoyable parts of my PhD journey. They’re a great way to take your mind off research while still staying connected to science.</p> <p>They also work wonderfully for outreach and teaching — and, honestly, they make fantastic desk decorations too!</p> <p>Whether you’re an educator, a researcher, or simply curious about materials, I hope these ideas inspire you to build your own crystal model and explore the beauty of materials science in a hands-on way.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a hands-on approach to science outreach and teaching materials science]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From a distant dream to reality - my AI4Science journey</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/my-AI4Science-journey/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From a distant dream to reality - my AI4Science journey"/><published>2025-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/my-AI4Science-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/my-AI4Science-journey/"><![CDATA[<p>Four years ago, doing a machine learning project felt like a distant dream. I didn’t know where to begin. Today, looking back at this long process, I want to share my journey of building an AI for Science (AI4Science) project completely from scratch.</p> <h3 id="not-your-usual-ml-project">Not your usual ML project</h3> <p>First, a disclaimer: this wasn’t the kind of deep learning project you’d typically see in a computer science department. I don’t have that kind of background or access to massive computational resources, nor do I aim to compete with people who build advanced algorithms. Their expertise is different, and often disconnected from science itself.</p> <p>For me, the foundation has always been materials science. Machine learning is just another tool—a way to accelerate discovery, much like spectroscopy, simulations, or microscopy. The real goal is to solve a scientific problem, not to “do machine learning” for its own sake.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/AI4Science-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/AI4Science-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/AI4Science-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/AI4Science.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="replicating-my-first-ml-study">Replicating my first ML study</h3> <p>My AI4Science journey stretched across my entire PhD—nearly four years. We began with the idea of designing better 2D perovskites using machine learning.</p> <p><em>(Quick explainer: perovskites are a rising star in solar energy materials. Some of them form 2D structures, where the atomic layers stack neatly like a sandwich. Others form non-2D structures, which are more disordered—imagine a Caesar salad instead of a sandwich.)</em></p> <p>The initial spark came from a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/jacs.1c05441">JACS paper</a> by Yiying Wu’s group, where they used machine learning to identify design rules for whether these materials form 2D or non-2D structures. My supervisor sent me the paper, and I quickly tried to replicate their results. Within three months, I had succeeded. At that time, I felt a bit smug—“hah, machine learning is so easy!”</p> <p>But I was wrong. Replication was straightforward because the method was already well-defined. The real challenge is choosing the right problem, defining meaningful input features, and picking target variables that matter scientifically. Originality is much harder.</p> <h3 id="when-data-runs-out">When data runs out</h3> <p>We wanted to push further and explore a less investigated subset of 2D perovskites—the DJ phase. But when I tried applying the same machine learning approach, I ran into a wall.</p> <p>The problem? Data. In the original study, they had about 86 data points from published experiments. For the DJ subset, I had only ~20—and the dataset was highly unbalanced. Machine learning simply wasn’t feasible.</p> <p>So, reluctantly, I set aside ML and turned to another approach.</p> <h3 id="if-not-ml-then-simulations">If not ML, then simulations</h3> <p>Since experimental data was scarce, we shifted to simulations to study the electronic structure of DJ perovskites (basically, how electrons behave inside the material, which determines whether it’s useful for devices).</p> <p>This was another long journey: finding computational resources, learning how to run the simulations, troubleshooting countless errors, and finally producing meaningful results.</p> <p>After more than half a year, I had my first full draft—a purely computational manuscript with no machine learning component. We spent another three months revising it, aiming for submission to PRL.</p> <h3 id="how-ml-found-its-way-back">How ML found its way back</h3> <p>Then, just before Christmas, I stumbled across an interesting <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-22611-4">Nature Communications paper</a>. It offered a clever way to scale up our dataset and translate material structures into features that could be understood by machine learning. Suddenly, I saw a way to bring ML back into the project.</p> <p>Within three months, we had completely reframed the study. What began as a simulation paper became a materials science project enhanced by machine learning.</p> <h3 id="the-long-road-to-submission">The long road to submission</h3> <p>Converting that simulation-focused draft into an ML-driven study took another eight months. Much of the time was spent digging deeper into the materials science side, asking whether the ML-predicted candidates could realistically be synthesized in the lab. Then came seven more months of back-and-forth revisions with my supervisor (unsurprising, since I was also finishing my thesis during this period).</p> <p>We’ve faced one desk rejection, and now the manuscript is under review at another journal. Fingers crossed that it finds its home soon.</p> <h3 id="what-ai4science-really-takes">What AI4Science really takes</h3> <p>Looking back at the figure above, you’ll notice my takeaway for you: ML itself wasn’t the hard part. Once I had the right dataset, I could complete a full ML workflow in an afternoon. The real difficulty lay in understanding the scientific problem—deciding whether ML was the right tool, and preparing the dataset in a way that made sense scientifically.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="AI"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a long way back to machine learning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A new chapter to my blog</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/blog-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new chapter to my blog"/><published>2025-08-17T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-17T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/blog-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/blog-update/"><![CDATA[<p>If you had asked me a year ago whether I’d ever have my own blog, I would’ve laughed and said, <em>I wish—but not likely!</em> I never thought of myself as “good at writing,” so the idea of keeping a blog felt like an impossible dream.</p> <p>But here we are—one year later.</p> <p>My friend Fabio once joked that everyone develops some unexpected hobbies during thesis writing (probably as a side effect of stress). For me, blogging turned out to be exactly that: a surprising, stress-born hobby that stuck.</p> <p>Back then, I was overwhelmed, and I had so many ideas buzzing around that I wanted to share—thoughts beyond just research. I wanted to remind myself (and maybe others) that I’m more than just my PhD project.</p> <p>Still, I was nervous. What if I couldn’t write well? What if nobody liked it? More importantly, I didn’t want blogging to feel like a burden. So I gave myself permission to treat it as an experiment, not a performance. No pressure, no audience—just a little corner of the internet where I could try things out.</p> <p>At first, I aimed for one post every two weeks. To my surprise, I actually enjoyed it. In fact, hitting “publish” on my very first post felt oddly thrilling—even though I wasn’t sure if anyone would ever read it.</p> <p>Fast forward: I’ve now written 20 posts. Sure, I slipped here and there, but I’ve been proud of my consistency. Along the way, I’ve figured out a workflow that mixes AI tools (thanks, ChatGPT!) with my own voice, and I’ve become more comfortable with writing in general.</p> <p>And now, a new chapter begins. I’ve finished my PhD, and my blog needs to evolve too. It’s no longer just an experiment. My new goal is to <strong>improve my writing</strong>, focus on quality, and slowly build a clearer “voice” for myself. I’d also like to think about what kind of content readers might actually enjoy—because maybe, just maybe, it’s time to share this blog more publicly. (Still working up the courage on that part!)</p> <p>I’ve also given the blog a fresh name. Goodbye <em>“Thoughts from a PhD Desk”</em>—hello <em>“Notes on Research, Teaching, and Life”</em>.</p> <p>That said, I’ve noticed a new challenge: choosing what to write about. My mind tends to jump between ideas, and sometimes I get stuck. So, I’m trying a new approach:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Slower schedule</strong>: Instead of posting every two weeks, I’ll publish once every four weeks. More time, less pressure.</li> <li><strong>More focus</strong>: I want to organize posts around themes that can grow into larger projects. For example, I want to try a recurring series called <em>“Data Science in the Wild”</em>, where I explore real-world datasets.</li> </ul> <p>So here’s to keeping at it. I’m genuinely proud that I’ve made it this far with blogging, and I’m excited (and a little nervous) about what comes next.</p> <p>And if you’re reading this—well, yay! That means my blog has actually gone public. Congrats to me for taking that leap, and thanks to you for being here.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life"/><category term="PhD-life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[after one year of blogging]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life after PhD</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/life-after-phd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life after PhD"/><published>2025-08-05T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-05T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/life-after-phd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/life-after-phd/"><![CDATA[<p>Five months ago, I submitted my PhD thesis. One month ago, I received my completion letter. It should have felt like a triumphant finale — the end of my student life and the start of the next chapter.</p> <p>Instead, it feels like standing in a dense fog, unable to see more than a few steps ahead.</p> <p>This post is for anyone else in that same limbo, and maybe for my future self. I don’t know if I’m making the “right” moves, or if I’ll one day wish I’d followed the traditional post-PhD script. But this is where I am right now.</p> <h3 id="that-whats-next-pressure">That “what’s next?” pressure</h3> <p>It’s the question I hear most often — and the one I quietly ask myself every day.</p> <p><em>So, what’s next? Have you started applying for jobs?</em></p> <p>I see peers securing postdocs or sending out dozens of applications. I haven’t done much of that. Not because I’m avoiding it, but because I don’t want to apply just for the sake of applying. I want to be intentional. I want a role I’m genuinely excited about, working under leadership I respect and can learn from.</p> <p>Part of my hesitation is practical: my work visa is still in process; my main PhD paper is navigating the long cycle of submission, rejection, and resubmission — and a publication would make me more competitive. I also want to present my research at conferences, both to share my results and to see where my work fits in the bigger picture.</p> <h3 id="the-slow-shift-toward-clarity">The slow shift toward clarity</h3> <p>Over the past few months, I’ve been experimenting and exploring. My aim: to discover what I can do, what I enjoy doing, and where that intersects with what the world needs. The fog in front of me is starting to lift — very slowly.</p> <p>Teaching has been a big part of that exploration. This term, I taught in two courses: one in my research area, and another in English communication. The second course, far outside my field, became a “gold standard” example of how to truly engage students. Both courses had incredible teaching teams, and I often felt like I was living the dream — working on projects that excite me, alongside people I deeply admire.</p> <p>This experience also overturned many of my doubts about teaching. I’ve sometimes worried that being “soft” is a weakness, but in the classroom, my patience and ability to explain clearly became real strengths. I enjoy it, and I’m good at it.</p> <p>I’ve also been breaking out of my “information box.” In my school, most people are either professors, postdocs, PhDs aiming for a postdoc, or PhDs determined to leave academia entirely. The prevailing wisdom seems to be that after your PhD, you either do a postdoc or jump into industry. But networking with academics from other schools have shown me otherwise. Even within universities, there are more paths than the well-trodden postdoc track.</p> <h3 id="where-my-compass-is-pointing">Where my compass is pointing</h3> <p>Right now, I’m more drawn to academia than industry. I love research, I thrive in the campus environment, and this term I’ve learned how much I enjoy teaching and connecting with students.</p> <p>My research passion is AI for science — especially using AI to accelerate scientific discovery, rather than simply producing more publications. I’m also curious about branching into biomedical and health applications, beyond my original field of materials science, though that idea is still taking shape.</p> <p>Beyond research, I want to communicate more — not just with peers in my narrow field, but with the wider public. I want my work to have impact, and I want to inspire the next generation of scientists. That naturally ties into education. After this term’s teaching, I can imagine transforming my research into courses that both inform and excite.</p> <p>For my next step, I’d like to combine research and teaching. Encouragingly, universities seem to be recognising and supporting this type of blended academic career path for PhD graduates. Recently, I came across the Early Career Academic Fellowship (ECAF) at UNSW — a role split evenly between teaching and research. It’s not well known in my own school, but finding it feels like a sign: there are more opportunities out there than I’ve been led to believe.</p> <p>So this is what I know so far. I’m still walking in the fog — but I think I’m moving toward the sunrise.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life"/><category term="PhD-life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[standing in the fog before the sunrise]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What was on my PhD desk?</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/whats-on-my-phd-desk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What was on my PhD desk?"/><published>2025-07-08T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/whats-on-my-phd-desk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/whats-on-my-phd-desk/"><![CDATA[<p>This month, I officially wrapped up my PhD journey! Last week, I packed up my desk and handed it back to the school. I wasn’t expecting it to feel so sentimental—but that little corner had been my space for years. It held not just my screens and notebooks, but the quiet progress of countless research days.</p> <p>So, I thought I’d mark the occasion with a behind-the-scenes post: what was on my PhD desk.</p> <h3 id="my-workspace">My workspace</h3> <p>Desk setup has always mattered to me—it shapes how productive and focused I feel. I was lucky to have a spot in one of the newest buildings on campus: floor-to-ceiling windows, beautiful natural light, and a generous desk with enough space to spread out.</p> <p>Although I sometimes worked in libraries or common study areas, my desk was my home base. My research was mostly computational, so my work lived on screens. A lot of it looked like… code. Lines and lines of code.</p> <p>I also happen to love productivity and desk setup content on YouTube—those “What’s On My Desk” videos are my guilty pleasure. Over time, I refined my own space, inspired by minimalism, but… let’s be honest. Some days it was more ‘creative chaos’ than curated workspace.</p> <p>Still, near the final stretch of my PhD, I did manage to create a version I was happy with. Here’s what it looked like—on a clean day, of course:</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/whats-on-my-desk.JPG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/whats-on-my-desk.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="screens-screens-screens">Screens, screens, screens</h3> <p>A big part of my desk setup was, unsurprisingly, screen real estate. My final screen setup looked like this:</p> <ul> <li>A MacBook Air (my main machine)</li> <li>An old iMac (used as a second screen)</li> <li>Occasionally, my iPad joined the lineup as a third screen</li> </ul> <p>For the first couple of years, I used just the MacBook. I liked the mobility—especially since I was still figuring out the office thermostat (pro tip: wearing too many winter layers indoors makes you sleepy).</p> <p>Then, midway through my third year, I stumbled on a treasure: an abandoned 2010 iMac sitting in the tearoom with a note that said “Good for parts.” It couldn’t run any modern apps, but it made for an excellent second monitor. Suddenly, coding became a lot easier.</p> <p>I did experiment with three screens—but for me, consistency mattered more than quantity. Switching setups always took a bit of adjustment.</p> <h3 id="desk-decorations">Desk decorations</h3> <p>Of course, a workspace isn’t just functional—it’s also personal.</p> <p>Everyone in our office decorated their desks in their own way—plushies, LEGO builds, Pop Mart figurines, tiny gacha machine toys. It made the room feel warm and lived-in.</p> <p>Here were my favourites:</p> <ul> <li>A Spring Festival couplet from our 2023 Lunar New Year event, organised by our student society, PGSOC. I wrote a little wish on mine—for smooth simulations and bug-free code.</li> <li>A magnetic 3D-printed perovskite model I designed and made myself. It started as a fun side project and later became part of our outreach demos at a science festival. After the event, it lived on the magnetic cabinet next to my desk—where I (or my officemates) could rearrange it into different crystal structures. Functional and fun!</li> </ul> <h3 id="how-not-to-fall-asleep-at-your-desk">How not to fall asleep at your desk</h3> <p>No matter how well the desk was set up, some days were just hard. We’ve all had those moments—staring at the screen, eyes glazing over. Here’s what helped me stay awake and focused:</p> <ul> <li>Temperature matters. For months, I couldn’t figure out why I was always sleepy. Turns out: I was simply overdressed. Fewer layers indoors, a warm coat for outside—problem solved.</li> <li> <p>Hydration. I bought a giant Stanley thermos (yes, that one—the one that looks like a liquid nitrogen tank). My goal was to drink the whole thing once a day. I didn’t make it on most days, but the regular bathroom breaks at least kept me moving.</p> </li> <li>Music. I never got into bulky over-ear headphones, so I used my AirPods. My go-to playlists were Peaceful Piano and lo-fi beats on spotify. I also loved the focus music on Headspace—it has built-in timers and gentle openings/endings, which really helped during thesis writing. (I only used it occasionally though—it’s a paid feature.)</li> <li>Movement. When all else failed, I stood up and wandered into the tearoom to chat with a friend. Sometimes, that’s all you need to reset.</li> </ul> <h3 id="signing-off">Signing off</h3> <p>Packing up my desk marked the end of my PhD era. That small space quietly held so much—late nights, tough problems, tiny breakthroughs, and the daily rituals that kept me going.</p> <p>But more than anything, what I’ll remember is the kindness. I’m deeply grateful to the administrative and academic staff at our school—Alan, Jane, and Qing especially—for always looking out for me with such warmth and support. I also feel incredibly lucky to have been part of our student society, PGSOC, where I served as a peer mentoring coordinator. That community became a meaningful part of my experience.</p> <p>So, here’s to the desk that saw it all—and to whatever comes next.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life"/><category term="PhD-life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a farewell to the space where I coded, wrote, and occasionally dozed off]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s really behind UNSW’s top 20 QS ranking?</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/QS-ranking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s really behind UNSW’s top 20 QS ranking?"/><published>2025-06-24T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-24T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/QS-ranking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/QS-ranking/"><![CDATA[<p>The latest QS World University Rankings just dropped, and guess what? My university — UNSW Sydney — has been ranked global top 20 again! Even more exciting, we’re now officially the second-highest ranked uni in Australia, just behind Melbourne and (yes!) ahead of the University of Sydney this year.</p> <p>Naturally, this made the rounds on campus pretty quickly. But as someone who’s currently teaching a data science course — and always on the lookout for interesting datasets — I couldn’t resist digging into the actual numbers behind the hype.</p> <p>Turns out, QS doesn’t just post pretty charts; they also make the raw data available. And if you give a data nerd a CSV… well, they’re going to analyze it.</p> <h3 id="how-do-qs-rankings-actually-work"><strong>How do QS rankings actually work?</strong></h3> <p>You might assume these rankings are just about research powerhouses or who’s publishing the most. But QS uses a mix of indicators that go beyond just academic output. Here’s the breakdown:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: left"><strong>Lens</strong></th> <th style="text-align: center"><strong>Weighting</strong></th> <th style="text-align: left"><strong>Indicator</strong></th> <th style="text-align: center"><strong>Weighting</strong></th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Research and Discovery</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">50%</td> <td style="text-align: left">Academic Reputation</td> <td style="text-align: center">30%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">Citations per Faculty</td> <td style="text-align: center">20%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Employability and Outcomes</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">20%</td> <td style="text-align: left">Employer Reputation</td> <td style="text-align: center">15%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">Employment Outcomes</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Global Engagement</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">15%</td> <td style="text-align: left">International Faculty Ratio</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">International Research Network</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">International Student Diversity</td> <td style="text-align: center">0%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">International Student Ratio</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Learning Experience</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">10%</td> <td style="text-align: left">Faculty Student Ratio</td> <td style="text-align: center">10%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Sustainability</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> <td style="text-align: left">Sustainability</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>So it’s not just about research. It’s also about who knows you, who hires your graduates, and how globally connected you are.</p> <h3 id="data-cleaning-focusing-on-the-top-500"><strong>Data cleaning: focusing on the top 500</strong></h3> <p>One thing I quickly noticed: universities lower down in the list often have patchy data. Missing values galore. So to keep things tidy, I focused my analysis on the top 500 universities — where the dataset is much more complete.</p> <p>From there, I looked at how different indicators relate to each other — and a few things really stood out:</p> <ul> <li>The <strong>Overall Score</strong> is most strongly correlated with <strong>Academic Reputation</strong>, followed by <strong>Employer Reputation</strong> — which is not suprising.</li> <li>Not shockingly, Academic and Employer Reputation are tightly linked (correlation coefficient = 0.79). Prestige matters — and it clearly carries over to job prospects.</li> <li>International Students Ratio and International Students Diversity show a near-perfect correlation (0.98!), which also aligns with common expectation.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="regional-trends-oceania-punches-above-its-weight"><strong>Regional trends: oceania punches above its weight</strong></h3> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Here’s where things got fun. I started breaking down scores by region, and a few trends jumped out:</p> <ul> <li>Asian universities generally have lower international student ratios — which aligns with my own experience as a Chinese student.</li> <li>Oceania (mostly Australia and New Zealand) stands out with massively high international student ratios — over 90% on average! That’s higher than both Europe and the Americas.</li> </ul> <p>A fun little outlier: the University of Johannesburg in South Africa has a whopping 60.1% international students — far higher than any other university on the continent.</p> <p>This focus on international engagement might help explain why Australian universities tend to do so well in global rankings. I mean… UNSW beat Yale this year. I still can’t quite believe that.</p> <p>But it’s not all good news.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>One metric where Oceania really lags? Faculty/Student Ratio — a rough proxy for class size and teaching support. Along with African universities, Oceania scores the lowest in this category.</p> <p>(That single outlier with excellent faculty/student support in our region? Massey University, New Zealand.)</p> <p>This might reflect funding models, growing enrolments, or how universities allocate teaching staff — but it’s a reminder that no university system is perfect.</p> <h3 id="so-what-really-drives-qs-rankings"><strong>So what really drives QS rankings?</strong></h3> <p>From this little data dive, it’s pretty clear that Academic Reputation is still the heavyweight in the QS formula — but global engagement plays a huge supporting role.</p> <p>And that favors universities like UNSW, which have built strong international strategies over the past few decades. On the flip side, even a well-known institution might struggle if class sizes balloon or their teaching support drops.</p> <h3 id="final-thoughts"><strong>Final thoughts</strong></h3> <p>As a proud UNSW alum and a slightly obsessive data nerd, I’ve always been curious about what’s behind the numbers we love to celebrate. We talk a lot about rankings, but rarely about what they mean.</p> <p>Looking at the data this way gives me a clearer sense of what makes UNSW strong — and where we could still improve.</p> <p>So next time someone throws out a ranking in conversation, maybe ask:</p> <blockquote> <p>“Cool — but what’s actually behind that number?”</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="data-science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a data-driven dive into what the rankings actually measure]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some thoughts about teaching</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/teaching/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some thoughts about teaching"/><published>2025-06-15T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-15T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/teaching</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/teaching/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve just finished my <strong>third week of teaching</strong>—and wow, what a journey it’s been already. I wanted to jot down some thoughts while they’re still fresh. If you’re brand new to teaching like me, maybe this reflection will help you feel a bit more prepared (or at least less alone!).</p> <p>When I first walked into a classroom as a tutor, I kind of assumed good teaching just <em>happened</em>—that some people were just naturally great at it. Especially the extroverted types who love being in the spotlight. But after going through the <em>Beginning to Teach</em> program at UNSW, I realized something really important: <strong>teaching isn’t just about being charismatic. It’s about being prepared—even when things don’t go as planned</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="teaching-isnt-a-conference-talk"><strong>Teaching Isn’t a Conference Talk</strong></h3> <p>One of the first big shifts I noticed was how different teaching is from giving a presentation. When I’m at a conference, I can walk through my slides however I like. If the audience follows—great. If not… well, that’s kind of on them.</p> <p>But teaching? Teaching is <em>not</em> that. At UNSW, there’s a huge focus on <strong>student-centered learning</strong>, which was very different from how I learned during my undergrad in Hong Kong. It’s not just about covering the material—it’s about checking in constantly, making sure students are engaged and following along, and adjusting if they’re not.</p> <p>I’ve learned that <strong>engagement isn’t optional—it’s the job</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="finding-my-teaching-style-and-letting-go-of-comparison"><strong>Finding My Teaching Style (And Letting Go of Comparison)</strong></h3> <p>In the beginning, I really struggled with comparison. Some of my colleagues—especially those with language teaching experience—seemed so confident and smooth in front of a classroom. I remember thinking, <em>“How can I ever be that good?”</em> During my first week, I was honestly quite discouraged. I even felt a bit sorry for my students, thinking they might learn more from someone with more experience.</p> <p>But here’s what I’ve come to realize: <strong>I don’t need to teach like them. I need to teach like me.</strong> And I <em>do</em> have my own strengths.</p> <p>I’m still figuring out what my teaching style looks like, but I’ve started leaning into what works for me—and what works for my students. I’m not the kind of person who enjoys lecturing at the front of the room for an hour straight. But I <em>am</em> good at creating smaller, interactive moments that help students feel more comfortable and involved.</p> <p>Plus, I’m still a student myself. I remember what it feels like to sit in those seats. I know what helps—and what doesn’t. And I have time and energy to really focus on supporting them.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="technology-is-my-friend"><strong>Technology Is My Friend</strong></h3> <p>The first couple of tutorials were really quiet—and I mean <em>awkwardly</em> quiet. When I asked a question, sometimes no one responded. I used to worry that meant students weren’t engaged or interested.</p> <p>But I’ve learned that <strong>quiet doesn’t mean disinterested</strong>—some students just don’t feel comfortable speaking out loud yet.</p> <p>That’s where tech comes in. Inspired by my friend’s online tutorials, I started using tools like <strong>Kahoot</strong>, <strong>Slido</strong>, and <strong>Microsoft Forms</strong>. They’re perfect for polls, check-ins, or anonymous questions. Students can engage by typing, which lowers the barrier and gets more people involved.</p> <p>It’s honestly been a game-changer.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="tech-glitches"><strong>Tech Glitches</strong></h3> <p>Speaking of tech… oh boy. That first week? It took me <em>forever</em> to get set up. Logging into the computer, finding the right slides, connecting my MacBook to the projector—it was a mess. I think I spent nearly 20 minutes just figuring things out.</p> <p>Now? I’ve got it down to under 5 minutes.</p> <p>Little wins!</p> <p>One trick I use all the time now is the <strong>“freeze screen”</strong> button. It lets me freeze the slide on the projector while I check notes or prep something quietly. Super useful.</p> <p>Also, <strong>don’t be afraid to ask for help</strong>. My teaching buddy Mariana was there for me during my first two weeks, and honestly, she saved my butt more than once.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="speaking-up-voice-and-confidence"><strong>Speaking Up: Voice and Confidence</strong></h3> <p>Another challenge: <strong>my voice is pretty soft</strong>. I found it scary to speak up in a big classroom at first, especially during those awkward first few minutes. But I’ve learned that once I get past the intro, it usually gets better.</p> <p>One tip that’s helped: I use a <strong>laser pointer</strong> so I can walk around instead of standing still at the front. It helps me feel more relaxed and gets me closer to the students, which makes speaking easier.</p> <p>Still working on this, but improving every week!</p> <hr/> <h3 id="time-management-less-is-more"><strong>Time Management: Less is More</strong></h3> <p>I always plan <em>way</em> too much content. I get excited about all the things I want to cover… and then run out of time.</p> <p>Now I’ve started thinking in terms of:</p> <ul> <li>What are the <strong>essential activities</strong> we <em>must</em> do?</li> <li>What’s <strong>nice to have</strong>, but skippable if needed?</li> </ul> <p>This has helped me slow down and create more space for discussion, questions, and flexibility. Honestly, it feels better for everyone.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="final-reminders-for-me-and-maybe-for-you-too"><strong>Final Reminders (For Me and Maybe for You Too)</strong></h3> <ul> <li><strong>Bring water.</strong> You’ll talk more than you think.</li> <li><strong>Relax before class.</strong> Take a breath, center yourself, and remind yourself you’re doing your best.</li> <li><strong>It’s okay not to be perfect.</strong> Every week is a chance to learn and grow.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[from someone who just started]]></summary></entry></feed>