<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-14T02:33:19+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/2025-10-14-perovskite-diy-model/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=""/><published>2025-10-14T02:33:19+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-14T02:33:19+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/2025-10-14-perovskite-diy-model</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/2025-10-14-perovskite-diy-model/"><![CDATA[<p>Most of my research happens inside a computer — simulating, visualizing, and analyzing atomic structures that exist only on a screen. But I’ve always loved handcrafts and making things in the real world. There’s something deeply satisfying about <em>holding</em> a model of the structure I usually see as colorful atoms on my monitor.</p> <p>During my PhD, I’ve been studying <strong>perovskites</strong> — a fascinating class of materials that appear everywhere from ceramics to solar cells. On the atomic scale, perovskites are built from repeating <strong>octahedra</strong> (eight-sided units) connected at their corners, forming a beautiful three-dimensional lattice.</p> <p>Over the years, I’ve explored several ways to <strong>bring this structure to life</strong> — blending science and creativity. In this post, I’ll share <strong>three hands-on ways</strong> to build your own perovskite crystal model:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Origami</strong> — fold your crystal lattice from paper</li> <li><strong>Knitting</strong> — create a soft, large-scale version</li> <li><strong>3D printing</strong> — design a durable, modular model for labs or demos</li> </ul> <p>Each method highlights a different aspect of the structure — geometry, scale, or modularity — and all are fun, tactile ways to explore materials science.</p> <h3 id="1-origami-perovskite"><strong>1. Origami Perovskite</strong></h3> <p><strong>Difficulty:</strong> ★☆☆ (Beginner)</p> <p><strong>Materials:</strong> Paper, thread</p> <p>My first and simplest experiment was the origami perovskite. All you need is paper and a bit of patience.</p> <p>Start by cutting paper into roughly a 3:1 rectangular shape and folding origami octahedra. You can follow this excellent <a href="https://www.thesprucecrafts.com/origami-octahedron-instructions-2540641">step-by-step guide</a>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/origami-perovskite-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> Once you’ve made a few octahedra, connect them at the corners using thread, gently tie them together to form a cubic network. I love this model because it’s flexible. You can tilt the octahedra to mimic the rotations that solid-state physicist observe in real perovskites. I originally made these to help visualize how octahedral tilts affect space group symmetry in perovskites. I used 30x10 cm rectangular paper, which makes the final model roughly **50 million times larger** than the atomic lattice! This is also a fantastic outreach activity. During the “Science in the Swamps” event with School of Chemistry at UNSW, we invited primary school kids and their families to fold their own octahedra. It was a bit tricky for smaller hands (and even some parents), but everyone loved seeing their creations come together into something scientific. In fact, I think the parents enjoyed it even more than the kids! You can find our outreach materials, including folding templates and a short intro to perovskites, here: [github link]. Another great variation comes from this [research-inspired project](https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jaume-Roqueta/publication/266383933_Origami_of_petovskite_structure/links/542e966d0cf277d58e8ec28b/Origami-of-petovskite-structure.pdf). Their workflow is similar but they build each octahedron from six seperate square pieces. I’ll have to try this method next time! ### 2. Knitted Perovskite **Difficulty:** ★★☆ (Intermediate) **Materials:** Yarn, knitting needles or crochet hooks, cardboard The next method takes perovskite modeling to a softer level — **knitting**! The idea was inspired by a wonderful project from **the University of Surrey**, where researchers and knitters collaborated to create a **2-meter-high** knitted perovskite, now proudly displayed in their Department of Chemistry. Here are a few articles about that project: [1](https://www.chemknits.com/2013/08/perovskite-crystal-project.html) [2](https://ladynthread.blogspot.com/2013/07/the-perovskite-project.html) [3](https://blogs.egu.eu/network/atomsi/2013/08/08/spinning-a-yarn-about-perovksite/) For my version, I used **8-ply yarn** to knit triangles (you can also crochet them). Then, I sewed eight triangles together to form an octahedron. Since the yarn shapes are too soft to hold on their own, I cut matching triangle pieces from cardboard, taped them together into an octahedron, and inserted them inside as supports. <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/knitting-perovskite-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/knitting-perovskite-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/knitting-perovskite-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/knitting-perovskite.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> This project is still ongoing. It’s time-consuming but incredibly fun. So far, I’ve made eight octahedra and plan to finish assembling them just in time for my graduation ceremony next month! ### **3. 3D-Printed Perovskite** **Difficulty:** ★★★ (Advanced) **Materials:** 3D printer, small magnetic balls, superglue Finally, my most robust and visually striking version — the **3D-printed perovskite**. This idea came from brainstorming with my cousin, [Zefang](), who’s an expert in 3D printing. I wanted a model that could be assembled and disassembled, rather than one fixed in place. <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-2.JPG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-2.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> The .stl files are avaliable here: [] When printing, it helps to orient one face flat on the bed for better stability. After printing, I added **5mm magnetic balls** at each corner, using superglue to secure them with their poles aligned along the axes. Be sure to alternate the poles—three corners with the north pole facing out and three with the south — so that the octahedra can connect without always repelling each other. The result is a **modular perovskite kit** that can be arranged into 0D, 1D, 2D or full 3D structures. My office mates and I had great fun assembling different configurations during coffee breaks! <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/3d-print-perovskite-3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> ### Final Thoughts Making these perovskite models has been one of the most rewarding part of my PhD journey. It's a reminder that science isn't only about code or equations. It can also be fun! Whether you're an educator, a researcher, or simply curious about materials, I hope these ideas inspire you to build your own perovskite! </div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">From a distant dream to reality – my AI4Science journey</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/my-AI4Science-journey/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From a distant dream to reality – my AI4Science journey"/><published>2025-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/my-AI4Science-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/my-AI4Science-journey/"><![CDATA[<p>Four years ago, doing a machine learning project felt like a distant dream. I didn’t know where to begin. Today, looking back at this long process, I want to share my journey of building an AI for Science (AI4Science) project completely from scratch.</p> <h3 id="not-your-usual-ml-project">Not your usual ML project</h3> <p>First, a disclaimer: this wasn’t the kind of deep learning project you’d typically see in a computer science department. I don’t have that kind of background or access to massive computational resources, nor do I aim to compete with people who build advanced algorithms. Their expertise is different, and often disconnected from science itself.</p> <p>For me, the foundation has always been materials science. Machine learning is just another tool—a way to accelerate discovery, much like spectroscopy, simulations, or microscopy. The real goal is to solve a scientific problem, not to “do machine learning” for its own sake.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/AI4Science-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/AI4Science-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/AI4Science-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/AI4Science.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="replicating-my-first-ml-study">Replicating my first ML study</h3> <p>My AI4Science journey stretched across my entire PhD—nearly four years. We began with the idea of designing better 2D perovskites using machine learning.</p> <p><em>(Quick explainer: perovskites are a rising star in solar energy materials. Some of them form 2D structures, where the atomic layers stack neatly like a sandwich. Others form non-2D structures, which are more disordered—imagine a Caesar salad instead of a sandwich.)</em></p> <p>The initial spark came from a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/jacs.1c05441">JACS paper</a> by Yiying Wu’s group, where they used machine learning to identify design rules for whether these materials form 2D or non-2D structures. My supervisor sent me the paper, and I quickly tried to replicate their results. Within three months, I had succeeded. At that time, I felt a bit smug—“hah, machine learning is so easy!”</p> <p>But I was wrong. Replication was straightforward because the method was already well-defined. The real challenge is choosing the right problem, defining meaningful input features, and picking target variables that matter scientifically. Originality is much harder.</p> <h3 id="when-data-runs-out">When data runs out</h3> <p>We wanted to push further and explore a less investigated subset of 2D perovskites—the DJ phase. But when I tried applying the same machine learning approach, I ran into a wall.</p> <p>The problem? Data. In the original study, they had about 86 data points from published experiments. For the DJ subset, I had only ~20—and the dataset was highly unbalanced. Machine learning simply wasn’t feasible.</p> <p>So, reluctantly, I set aside ML and turned to another approach.</p> <h3 id="if-not-ml-then-simulations">If not ML, then simulations</h3> <p>Since experimental data was scarce, we shifted to simulations to study the electronic structure of DJ perovskites (basically, how electrons behave inside the material, which determines whether it’s useful for devices).</p> <p>This was another long journey: finding computational resources, learning how to run the simulations, troubleshooting countless errors, and finally producing meaningful results.</p> <p>After more than half a year, I had my first full draft—a purely computational manuscript with no machine learning component. We spent another three months revising it, aiming for submission to PRL.</p> <h3 id="how-ml-found-its-way-back">How ML found its way back</h3> <p>Then, just before Christmas, I stumbled across an interesting <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-22611-4">Nature Communications paper</a>. It offered a clever way to scale up our dataset and translate material structures into features that could be understood by machine learning. Suddenly, I saw a way to bring ML back into the project.</p> <p>Within three months, we had completely reframed the study. What began as a simulation paper became a materials science project enhanced by machine learning.</p> <h3 id="the-long-road-to-submission">The long road to submission</h3> <p>Converting that simulation-focused draft into an ML-driven study took another eight months. Much of the time was spent digging deeper into the materials science side, asking whether the ML-predicted candidates could realistically be synthesized in the lab. Then came seven more months of back-and-forth revisions with my supervisor (unsurprising, since I was also finishing my thesis during this period).</p> <p>We’ve faced one desk rejection, and now the manuscript is under review at another journal. Fingers crossed that it finds its home soon.</p> <h3 id="what-ai4science-really-takes">What AI4Science really takes</h3> <p>Looking back at the figure above, you’ll notice my takeaway for you: ML itself wasn’t the hard part. Once I had the right dataset, I could complete a full ML workflow in an afternoon. The real difficulty lay in understanding the scientific problem—deciding whether ML was the right tool, and preparing the dataset in a way that made sense scientifically.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="AI"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a long way back to machine learning]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A new chapter to my blog</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/blog-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new chapter to my blog"/><published>2025-08-17T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-17T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/blog-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/blog-update/"><![CDATA[<p>If you had asked me a year ago whether I’d ever have my own blog, I would’ve laughed and said, <em>I wish—but not likely!</em> I never thought of myself as “good at writing,” so the idea of keeping a blog felt like an impossible dream.</p> <p>But here we are—one year later.</p> <p>My friend Fabio once joked that everyone develops some unexpected hobbies during thesis writing (probably as a side effect of stress). For me, blogging turned out to be exactly that: a surprising, stress-born hobby that stuck.</p> <p>Back then, I was overwhelmed, and I had so many ideas buzzing around that I wanted to share—thoughts beyond just research. I wanted to remind myself (and maybe others) that I’m more than just my PhD project.</p> <p>Still, I was nervous. What if I couldn’t write well? What if nobody liked it? More importantly, I didn’t want blogging to feel like a burden. So I gave myself permission to treat it as an experiment, not a performance. No pressure, no audience—just a little corner of the internet where I could try things out.</p> <p>At first, I aimed for one post every two weeks. To my surprise, I actually enjoyed it. In fact, hitting “publish” on my very first post felt oddly thrilling—even though I wasn’t sure if anyone would ever read it.</p> <p>Fast forward: I’ve now written 20 posts. Sure, I slipped here and there, but I’ve been proud of my consistency. Along the way, I’ve figured out a workflow that mixes AI tools (thanks, ChatGPT!) with my own voice, and I’ve become more comfortable with writing in general.</p> <p>And now, a new chapter begins. I’ve finished my PhD, and my blog needs to evolve too. It’s no longer just an experiment. My new goal is to <strong>improve my writing</strong>, focus on quality, and slowly build a clearer “voice” for myself. I’d also like to think about what kind of content readers might actually enjoy—because maybe, just maybe, it’s time to share this blog more publicly. (Still working up the courage on that part!)</p> <p>I’ve also given the blog a fresh name. Goodbye <em>“Thoughts from a PhD Desk”</em>—hello <em>“Notes on Research, Teaching, and Life”</em>.</p> <p>That said, I’ve noticed a new challenge: choosing what to write about. My mind tends to jump between ideas, and sometimes I get stuck. So, I’m trying a new approach:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Slower schedule</strong>: Instead of posting every two weeks, I’ll publish once every four weeks. More time, less pressure.</li> <li><strong>More focus</strong>: I want to organize posts around themes that can grow into larger projects. For example, I want to try a recurring series called <em>“Data Science in the Wild”</em>, where I explore real-world datasets.</li> </ul> <p>So here’s to keeping at it. I’m genuinely proud that I’ve made it this far with blogging, and I’m excited (and a little nervous) about what comes next.</p> <p>And if you’re reading this—well, yay! That means my blog has actually gone public. Congrats to me for taking that leap, and thanks to you for being here.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life"/><category term="PhD-life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[after one year of blogging]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life after PhD</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/life-after-phd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life after PhD"/><published>2025-08-05T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-05T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/life-after-phd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/life-after-phd/"><![CDATA[<p>Five months ago, I submitted my PhD thesis. One month ago, I received my completion letter. It should have felt like a triumphant finale — the end of my student life and the start of the next chapter.</p> <p>Instead, it feels like standing in a dense fog, unable to see more than a few steps ahead.</p> <p>This post is for anyone else in that same limbo, and maybe for my future self. I don’t know if I’m making the “right” moves, or if I’ll one day wish I’d followed the traditional post-PhD script. But this is where I am right now.</p> <h3 id="that-whats-next-pressure">That “what’s next?” pressure</h3> <p>It’s the question I hear most often — and the one I quietly ask myself every day.</p> <p><em>So, what’s next? Have you started applying for jobs?</em></p> <p>I see peers securing postdocs or sending out dozens of applications. I haven’t done much of that. Not because I’m avoiding it, but because I don’t want to apply just for the sake of applying. I want to be intentional. I want a role I’m genuinely excited about, working under leadership I respect and can learn from.</p> <p>Part of my hesitation is practical: my work visa is still in process; my main PhD paper is navigating the long cycle of submission, rejection, and resubmission — and a publication would make me more competitive. I also want to present my research at conferences, both to share my results and to see where my work fits in the bigger picture.</p> <h3 id="the-slow-shift-toward-clarity">The slow shift toward clarity</h3> <p>Over the past few months, I’ve been experimenting and exploring. My aim: to discover what I can do, what I enjoy doing, and where that intersects with what the world needs. The fog in front of me is starting to lift — very slowly.</p> <p>Teaching has been a big part of that exploration. This term, I taught in two courses: one in my research area, and another in English communication. The second course, far outside my field, became a “gold standard” example of how to truly engage students. Both courses had incredible teaching teams, and I often felt like I was living the dream — working on projects that excite me, alongside people I deeply admire.</p> <p>This experience also overturned many of my doubts about teaching. I’ve sometimes worried that being “soft” is a weakness, but in the classroom, my patience and ability to explain clearly became real strengths. I enjoy it, and I’m good at it.</p> <p>I’ve also been breaking out of my “information box.” In my school, most people are either professors, postdocs, PhDs aiming for a postdoc, or PhDs determined to leave academia entirely. The prevailing wisdom seems to be that after your PhD, you either do a postdoc or jump into industry. But networking with academics from other schools have shown me otherwise. Even within universities, there are more paths than the well-trodden postdoc track.</p> <h3 id="where-my-compass-is-pointing">Where my compass is pointing</h3> <p>Right now, I’m more drawn to academia than industry. I love research, I thrive in the campus environment, and this term I’ve learned how much I enjoy teaching and connecting with students.</p> <p>My research passion is AI for science — especially using AI to accelerate scientific discovery, rather than simply producing more publications. I’m also curious about branching into biomedical and health applications, beyond my original field of materials science, though that idea is still taking shape.</p> <p>Beyond research, I want to communicate more — not just with peers in my narrow field, but with the wider public. I want my work to have impact, and I want to inspire the next generation of scientists. That naturally ties into education. After this term’s teaching, I can imagine transforming my research into courses that both inform and excite.</p> <p>For my next step, I’d like to combine research and teaching. Encouragingly, universities seem to be recognising and supporting this type of blended academic career path for PhD graduates. Recently, I came across the Early Career Academic Fellowship (ECAF) at UNSW — a role split evenly between teaching and research. It’s not well known in my own school, but finding it feels like a sign: there are more opportunities out there than I’ve been led to believe.</p> <p>So this is what I know so far. I’m still walking in the fog — but I think I’m moving toward the sunrise.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life"/><category term="PhD-life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[standing in the fog before the sunrise]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What was on my PhD desk?</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/whats-on-my-phd-desk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What was on my PhD desk?"/><published>2025-07-08T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/whats-on-my-phd-desk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/whats-on-my-phd-desk/"><![CDATA[<p>This month, I officially wrapped up my PhD journey! Last week, I packed up my desk and handed it back to the school. I wasn’t expecting it to feel so sentimental—but that little corner had been my space for years. It held not just my screens and notebooks, but the quiet progress of countless research days.</p> <p>So, I thought I’d mark the occasion with a behind-the-scenes post: what was on my PhD desk.</p> <h3 id="my-workspace">My workspace</h3> <p>Desk setup has always mattered to me—it shapes how productive and focused I feel. I was lucky to have a spot in one of the newest buildings on campus: floor-to-ceiling windows, beautiful natural light, and a generous desk with enough space to spread out.</p> <p>Although I sometimes worked in libraries or common study areas, my desk was my home base. My research was mostly computational, so my work lived on screens. A lot of it looked like… code. Lines and lines of code.</p> <p>I also happen to love productivity and desk setup content on YouTube—those “What’s On My Desk” videos are my guilty pleasure. Over time, I refined my own space, inspired by minimalism, but… let’s be honest. Some days it was more ‘creative chaos’ than curated workspace.</p> <p>Still, near the final stretch of my PhD, I did manage to create a version I was happy with. Here’s what it looked like—on a clean day, of course:</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/whats-on-my-desk.JPG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/whats-on-my-desk.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="screens-screens-screens">Screens, screens, screens</h3> <p>A big part of my desk setup was, unsurprisingly, screen real estate. My final screen setup looked like this:</p> <ul> <li>A MacBook Air (my main machine)</li> <li>An old iMac (used as a second screen)</li> <li>Occasionally, my iPad joined the lineup as a third screen</li> </ul> <p>For the first couple of years, I used just the MacBook. I liked the mobility—especially since I was still figuring out the office thermostat (pro tip: wearing too many winter layers indoors makes you sleepy).</p> <p>Then, midway through my third year, I stumbled on a treasure: an abandoned 2010 iMac sitting in the tearoom with a note that said “Good for parts.” It couldn’t run any modern apps, but it made for an excellent second monitor. Suddenly, coding became a lot easier.</p> <p>I did experiment with three screens—but for me, consistency mattered more than quantity. Switching setups always took a bit of adjustment.</p> <h3 id="desk-decorations">Desk decorations</h3> <p>Of course, a workspace isn’t just functional—it’s also personal.</p> <p>Everyone in our office decorated their desks in their own way—plushies, LEGO builds, Pop Mart figurines, tiny gacha machine toys. It made the room feel warm and lived-in.</p> <p>Here were my favourites:</p> <ul> <li>A Spring Festival couplet from our 2023 Lunar New Year event, organised by our student society, PGSOC. I wrote a little wish on mine—for smooth simulations and bug-free code.</li> <li>A magnetic 3D-printed perovskite model I designed and made myself. It started as a fun side project and later became part of our outreach demos at a science festival. After the event, it lived on the magnetic cabinet next to my desk—where I (or my officemates) could rearrange it into different crystal structures. Functional and fun!</li> </ul> <h3 id="how-not-to-fall-asleep-at-your-desk">How not to fall asleep at your desk</h3> <p>No matter how well the desk was set up, some days were just hard. We’ve all had those moments—staring at the screen, eyes glazing over. Here’s what helped me stay awake and focused:</p> <ul> <li>Temperature matters. For months, I couldn’t figure out why I was always sleepy. Turns out: I was simply overdressed. Fewer layers indoors, a warm coat for outside—problem solved.</li> <li> <p>Hydration. I bought a giant Stanley thermos (yes, that one—the one that looks like a liquid nitrogen tank). My goal was to drink the whole thing once a day. I didn’t make it on most days, but the regular bathroom breaks at least kept me moving.</p> </li> <li>Music. I never got into bulky over-ear headphones, so I used my AirPods. My go-to playlists were Peaceful Piano and lo-fi beats on spotify. I also loved the focus music on Headspace—it has built-in timers and gentle openings/endings, which really helped during thesis writing. (I only used it occasionally though—it’s a paid feature.)</li> <li>Movement. When all else failed, I stood up and wandered into the tearoom to chat with a friend. Sometimes, that’s all you need to reset.</li> </ul> <h3 id="signing-off">Signing off</h3> <p>Packing up my desk marked the end of my PhD era. That small space quietly held so much—late nights, tough problems, tiny breakthroughs, and the daily rituals that kept me going.</p> <p>But more than anything, what I’ll remember is the kindness. I’m deeply grateful to the administrative and academic staff at our school—Alan, Jane, and Qing especially—for always looking out for me with such warmth and support. I also feel incredibly lucky to have been part of our student society, PGSOC, where I served as a peer mentoring coordinator. That community became a meaningful part of my experience.</p> <p>So, here’s to the desk that saw it all—and to whatever comes next.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life"/><category term="PhD-life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a farewell to the space where I coded, wrote, and occasionally dozed off]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s really behind UNSW’s top 20 QS ranking?</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/QS-ranking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s really behind UNSW’s top 20 QS ranking?"/><published>2025-06-24T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-24T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/QS-ranking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/QS-ranking/"><![CDATA[<p>The latest QS World University Rankings just dropped, and guess what? My university — UNSW Sydney — has been ranked global top 20 again! Even more exciting, we’re now officially the second-highest ranked uni in Australia, just behind Melbourne and (yes!) ahead of the University of Sydney this year.</p> <p>Naturally, this made the rounds on campus pretty quickly. But as someone who’s currently teaching a data science course — and always on the lookout for interesting datasets — I couldn’t resist digging into the actual numbers behind the hype.</p> <p>Turns out, QS doesn’t just post pretty charts; they also make the raw data available. And if you give a data nerd a CSV… well, they’re going to analyze it.</p> <h3 id="how-do-qs-rankings-actually-work"><strong>How do QS rankings actually work?</strong></h3> <p>You might assume these rankings are just about research powerhouses or who’s publishing the most. But QS uses a mix of indicators that go beyond just academic output. Here’s the breakdown:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: left"><strong>Lens</strong></th> <th style="text-align: center"><strong>Weighting</strong></th> <th style="text-align: left"><strong>Indicator</strong></th> <th style="text-align: center"><strong>Weighting</strong></th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Research and Discovery</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">50%</td> <td style="text-align: left">Academic Reputation</td> <td style="text-align: center">30%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">Citations per Faculty</td> <td style="text-align: center">20%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Employability and Outcomes</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">20%</td> <td style="text-align: left">Employer Reputation</td> <td style="text-align: center">15%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">Employment Outcomes</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Global Engagement</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">15%</td> <td style="text-align: left">International Faculty Ratio</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">International Research Network</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">International Student Diversity</td> <td style="text-align: center">0%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"> </td> <td style="text-align: center"> </td> <td style="text-align: left">International Student Ratio</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Learning Experience</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">10%</td> <td style="text-align: left">Faculty Student Ratio</td> <td style="text-align: center">10%</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Sustainability</strong></td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> <td style="text-align: left">Sustainability</td> <td style="text-align: center">5%</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>So it’s not just about research. It’s also about who knows you, who hires your graduates, and how globally connected you are.</p> <h3 id="data-cleaning-focusing-on-the-top-500"><strong>Data cleaning: focusing on the top 500</strong></h3> <p>One thing I quickly noticed: universities lower down in the list often have patchy data. Missing values galore. So to keep things tidy, I focused my analysis on the top 500 universities — where the dataset is much more complete.</p> <p>From there, I looked at how different indicators relate to each other — and a few things really stood out:</p> <ul> <li>The <strong>Overall Score</strong> is most strongly correlated with <strong>Academic Reputation</strong>, followed by <strong>Employer Reputation</strong> — which is not suprising.</li> <li>Not shockingly, Academic and Employer Reputation are tightly linked (correlation coefficient = 0.79). Prestige matters — and it clearly carries over to job prospects.</li> <li>International Students Ratio and International Students Diversity show a near-perfect correlation (0.98!), which also aligns with common expectation.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h3 id="regional-trends-oceania-punches-above-its-weight"><strong>Regional trends: oceania punches above its weight</strong></h3> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-3.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Here’s where things got fun. I started breaking down scores by region, and a few trends jumped out:</p> <ul> <li>Asian universities generally have lower international student ratios — which aligns with my own experience as a Chinese student.</li> <li>Oceania (mostly Australia and New Zealand) stands out with massively high international student ratios — over 90% on average! That’s higher than both Europe and the Americas.</li> </ul> <p>A fun little outlier: the University of Johannesburg in South Africa has a whopping 60.1% international students — far higher than any other university on the continent.</p> <p>This focus on international engagement might help explain why Australian universities tend to do so well in global rankings. I mean… UNSW beat Yale this year. I still can’t quite believe that.</p> <p>But it’s not all good news.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-8 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_figure/qs-ranking-2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>One metric where Oceania really lags? Faculty/Student Ratio — a rough proxy for class size and teaching support. Along with African universities, Oceania scores the lowest in this category.</p> <p>(That single outlier with excellent faculty/student support in our region? Massey University, New Zealand.)</p> <p>This might reflect funding models, growing enrolments, or how universities allocate teaching staff — but it’s a reminder that no university system is perfect.</p> <h3 id="so-what-really-drives-qs-rankings"><strong>So what really drives QS rankings?</strong></h3> <p>From this little data dive, it’s pretty clear that Academic Reputation is still the heavyweight in the QS formula — but global engagement plays a huge supporting role.</p> <p>And that favors universities like UNSW, which have built strong international strategies over the past few decades. On the flip side, even a well-known institution might struggle if class sizes balloon or their teaching support drops.</p> <h3 id="final-thoughts"><strong>Final thoughts</strong></h3> <p>As a proud UNSW alum and a slightly obsessive data nerd, I’ve always been curious about what’s behind the numbers we love to celebrate. We talk a lot about rankings, but rarely about what they mean.</p> <p>Looking at the data this way gives me a clearer sense of what makes UNSW strong — and where we could still improve.</p> <p>So next time someone throws out a ranking in conversation, maybe ask:</p> <blockquote> <p>“Cool — but what’s actually behind that number?”</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="data-science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a data-driven dive into what the rankings actually measure]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some thoughts about teaching</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/teaching/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some thoughts about teaching"/><published>2025-06-15T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-15T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/teaching</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/teaching/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve just finished my <strong>third week of teaching</strong>—and wow, what a journey it’s been already. I wanted to jot down some thoughts while they’re still fresh. If you’re brand new to teaching like me, maybe this reflection will help you feel a bit more prepared (or at least less alone!).</p> <p>When I first walked into a classroom as a tutor, I kind of assumed good teaching just <em>happened</em>—that some people were just naturally great at it. Especially the extroverted types who love being in the spotlight. But after going through the <em>Beginning to Teach</em> program at UNSW, I realized something really important: <strong>teaching isn’t just about being charismatic. It’s about being prepared—even when things don’t go as planned</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="teaching-isnt-a-conference-talk"><strong>Teaching Isn’t a Conference Talk</strong></h3> <p>One of the first big shifts I noticed was how different teaching is from giving a presentation. When I’m at a conference, I can walk through my slides however I like. If the audience follows—great. If not… well, that’s kind of on them.</p> <p>But teaching? Teaching is <em>not</em> that. At UNSW, there’s a huge focus on <strong>student-centered learning</strong>, which was very different from how I learned during my undergrad in Hong Kong. It’s not just about covering the material—it’s about checking in constantly, making sure students are engaged and following along, and adjusting if they’re not.</p> <p>I’ve learned that <strong>engagement isn’t optional—it’s the job</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="finding-my-teaching-style-and-letting-go-of-comparison"><strong>Finding My Teaching Style (And Letting Go of Comparison)</strong></h3> <p>In the beginning, I really struggled with comparison. Some of my colleagues—especially those with language teaching experience—seemed so confident and smooth in front of a classroom. I remember thinking, <em>“How can I ever be that good?”</em> During my first week, I was honestly quite discouraged. I even felt a bit sorry for my students, thinking they might learn more from someone with more experience.</p> <p>But here’s what I’ve come to realize: <strong>I don’t need to teach like them. I need to teach like me.</strong> And I <em>do</em> have my own strengths.</p> <p>I’m still figuring out what my teaching style looks like, but I’ve started leaning into what works for me—and what works for my students. I’m not the kind of person who enjoys lecturing at the front of the room for an hour straight. But I <em>am</em> good at creating smaller, interactive moments that help students feel more comfortable and involved.</p> <p>Plus, I’m still a student myself. I remember what it feels like to sit in those seats. I know what helps—and what doesn’t. And I have time and energy to really focus on supporting them.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="technology-is-my-friend"><strong>Technology Is My Friend</strong></h3> <p>The first couple of tutorials were really quiet—and I mean <em>awkwardly</em> quiet. When I asked a question, sometimes no one responded. I used to worry that meant students weren’t engaged or interested.</p> <p>But I’ve learned that <strong>quiet doesn’t mean disinterested</strong>—some students just don’t feel comfortable speaking out loud yet.</p> <p>That’s where tech comes in. Inspired by my friend’s online tutorials, I started using tools like <strong>Kahoot</strong>, <strong>Slido</strong>, and <strong>Microsoft Forms</strong>. They’re perfect for polls, check-ins, or anonymous questions. Students can engage by typing, which lowers the barrier and gets more people involved.</p> <p>It’s honestly been a game-changer.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="tech-glitches"><strong>Tech Glitches</strong></h3> <p>Speaking of tech… oh boy. That first week? It took me <em>forever</em> to get set up. Logging into the computer, finding the right slides, connecting my MacBook to the projector—it was a mess. I think I spent nearly 20 minutes just figuring things out.</p> <p>Now? I’ve got it down to under 5 minutes.</p> <p>Little wins!</p> <p>One trick I use all the time now is the <strong>“freeze screen”</strong> button. It lets me freeze the slide on the projector while I check notes or prep something quietly. Super useful.</p> <p>Also, <strong>don’t be afraid to ask for help</strong>. My teaching buddy Mariana was there for me during my first two weeks, and honestly, she saved my butt more than once.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="speaking-up-voice-and-confidence"><strong>Speaking Up: Voice and Confidence</strong></h3> <p>Another challenge: <strong>my voice is pretty soft</strong>. I found it scary to speak up in a big classroom at first, especially during those awkward first few minutes. But I’ve learned that once I get past the intro, it usually gets better.</p> <p>One tip that’s helped: I use a <strong>laser pointer</strong> so I can walk around instead of standing still at the front. It helps me feel more relaxed and gets me closer to the students, which makes speaking easier.</p> <p>Still working on this, but improving every week!</p> <hr/> <h3 id="time-management-less-is-more"><strong>Time Management: Less is More</strong></h3> <p>I always plan <em>way</em> too much content. I get excited about all the things I want to cover… and then run out of time.</p> <p>Now I’ve started thinking in terms of:</p> <ul> <li>What are the <strong>essential activities</strong> we <em>must</em> do?</li> <li>What’s <strong>nice to have</strong>, but skippable if needed?</li> </ul> <p>This has helped me slow down and create more space for discussion, questions, and flexibility. Honestly, it feels better for everyone.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="final-reminders-for-me-and-maybe-for-you-too"><strong>Final Reminders (For Me and Maybe for You Too)</strong></h3> <ul> <li><strong>Bring water.</strong> You’ll talk more than you think.</li> <li><strong>Relax before class.</strong> Take a breath, center yourself, and remind yourself you’re doing your best.</li> <li><strong>It’s okay not to be perfect.</strong> Every week is a chance to learn and grow.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[from someone who just started]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From Jupyter notebook to website</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/jupyter-book/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Jupyter notebook to website"/><published>2025-05-27T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-27T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/jupyter-book</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/jupyter-book/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I started my teaching journey by helping out with a data science course. That got me wondering–how do people actually teach Python and machine learning to complete beginners?</p> <p>To find out, I began looking at how others structure their course materials. I came across two fantastic examples: Professor Aron Walsh’s <a href="https://aronwalsh.github.io/MLforMaterials">Machine Learning for Materials</a> at UCL and Professor Zachary Ulissi’s <a href="https://ulissigroup.cheme.cmu.edu/F22-06-325/index.html">Numerical Methods and ML for Chemical Engineers</a> at CMU. Their course websites are beautifully organized, with lecture slides and interactive Jupyter Notebooks available directly in the browser.</p> <p>As someone who uses Python and machine learning daily in my own research, I found it fascinating to see how these tools are introduced in a classroom setting. I’ve mostly been self-taught, so I’d never thought much about <em>how</em> to teach them from the ground up.</p> <p>What really stood out to me was that both courses have a fully functional website where all their teaching materials—including Jupyter Notebooks—are not only hosted but can be explored interactively. That’s when I discovered the secret weapon behind them: <strong>Jupyter Book</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="what-is-jupyter-book"><strong>What is Jupyter Book?</strong></h3> <p><a href="https://jupyterbook.org/">Jupyter Book</a> is a Python library that turns collections of Markdown files and Jupyter Notebooks into a structured HTML website. You can organize content into chapters and sections, just like a digital textbook.</p> <p>The best part? Readers can view the notebook outputs directly in the browser without needing to install anything or set up a cloud environment. Even better, you can enable <strong>live coding</strong> using platforms like <em>Binder</em>, <em>Google Colab</em>, or even <em>Thebe</em> to run code right on the website.</p> <p>I built a mock course site called <em>Personalised Programming Language Enhancement</em> using Jupyter Book–feel free to check it out <a href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/PPLE/">here</a>.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="how-i-built-my-jupyter-book"><strong>How I built my Jupyter Book</strong></h3> <p><strong>1. Install Jupyter Book</strong></p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>pip <span class="nb">install</span> <span class="nt">-U</span> jupyter-book
</code></pre></div></div> <p><strong>2. Create a sample book</strong></p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>jupyter-book create mynewbook/
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This generates a folder structure like this:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>├── _config.yml          # Book settings (title, author, theme, etc.)
├── _toc.yml             # Table of contents (page structure)
├── intro.md             # First page of your book
├── notebooks.ipynb      # Sample notebook
├── markdown.md          # Sample markdown content
├── requirements.txt     # Python packages for running the book
</code></pre></div></div> <p><strong>3. Modify key files</strong></p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code>: Set your book’s title, author, and theme.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_toc.yml</code>: Define the structure and order of pages/sections.</li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">requirements.txt</code>: List any Python packages your notebooks use.</li> </ul> <p><strong>4. Build your book</strong></p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>jupyter-book build mynewbook/
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This will generate an <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_build/</code> folder with all your HTML files that you can preview locally.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="hosting-on-github-pages"><strong>Hosting on GitHub Pages</strong></h3> <p>There are two main ways to publish your book:</p> <p><strong>1. Manual:</strong> Push the HTML files in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_build/</code> to your GitHub repository.</p> <p><strong>2. Automated (my favorite!):</strong> Use GitHub Actions to automatically build and deploy the book every time you push updates.</p> <p>Here’s how I set it up:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Add a GitHub Actions file: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.github/workflows/deploy.yml</code> (You can use this official <a href="https://jupyterbook.org/en/stable/publish/gh-pages.html">template</a> or check out mine <a href="https://github.com/yongxinlyu/PPLE/blob/main/.github/workflows/deploy.yml">here</a>.)</p> </li> <li>Go to your repository <strong>Settings</strong>: <ul> <li>Under <strong>Actions &gt; General</strong>, set workflow permissions to “Read and write.”</li> <li>Under <strong>Pages</strong>, choose to deploy from the gh-pages branch.</li> </ul> </li> <li>I still build the site locally to test it before pushing changes, but I ignore the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_build/</code> folder using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.gitignore</code> to keep the repository clean.</li> </ul> <p>Once it’s set up, GitHub will host your site and give you a public URL–perfect for sharing with students or collaborators!</p> <hr/> <h3 id="make-it-interactive"><strong>Make it interactive</strong></h3> <p>You can add live execution options with just a few lines in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code>:</p> <div class="language-yml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">launch_buttons</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="na">colab_url</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">https://colab.research.google.com"</span>
  <span class="na">binderhub_url</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">https://mybinder.org"</span>
  <span class="na">thebe</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="kc">true</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This will add buttons to each notebook page so users can open the content directly in Colab, Binder, or even execute it live in the browser using Thebe.</p> <p>Note: you have to make the github repository public to enable these options.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="final-thoughts"><strong>Final thoughts</strong></h3> <p>If you’re curious to see what others have done with Jupyter Book, check out this gallery: <a href="https://executablebooks.org/en/latest/gallery/">Executable Books Gallery</a>.</p> <p>While preparing this data science course, I’ve also been digging around for real-world datasets from the literature. Honestly, I was surprised at how <em>hard</em> it is to find well-organized, usable code and data–even when people say they’ve made them publicly available.</p> <p>Most of the time, research code on GitHub is hard to read, lacks documentation, or is impossible to reproduce. That’s why I believe tools like Jupyter Book are a step in the right direction. They make it easier to share knowledge-—even with people who aren’t experienced coders. I hope more researchers give it a try and help make science more open, accessible, and reproducible.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[sharing teaching materials with jupyter-book]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ocean therapy at coogee</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/ocean-swim/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ocean therapy at coogee"/><published>2025-05-13T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-13T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/ocean-swim</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/ocean-swim/"><![CDATA[<p>If I had to pick one beach in the world to keep returning to, it would be Coogee. Hands down, my all-time favourite. There’s something about it—maybe the mix of raw ocean energy and the tucked-away rock pools, or maybe just the feeling I get when I’m there. These days, I’ve been doing what I call “ocean therapy” at Coogee, and I want to share a little slice of that experience with you.</p> <p>Ocean therapy, in its simplest form, is this: get into the water, head to toe. That’s it. No gear, no goals, no pressure. Just you and the ocean.</p> <p>Unlike most people who flock to the beach in summer, I actually prefer going during the colder months. Yes, even in winter! The water usually sits between 18°C and 20°C, and the beach feels like it’s taken a deep breath—quiet, calm, and almost meditative without the summer crowds.</p> <p>Some friends think I’m a bit mad. “Isn’t it freezing?” they ask. Well, yes. That’s the point. The cold jolts you awake in the best way. It’s like drinking an espresso for your whole body. Cold water makes me feel present and alive—it brings me out of my thoughts and straight into the moment.</p> <p>Once I’m in, I don’t do much. A bit of gentle swimming, a little floating, and often just leaning on the edge of the rock pool, elbows resting on the seaweed-covered stones (they feel like a green velvet blanket), watching the waves crash beyond. It’s grounding and hypnotic in the best way.</p> <p>One of my unexpected joys? Watching other people get into the cold water. Especially in winter. There’s a universal moment of hesitation, a deep breath, a burst of bravery—and then the cold hits. It’s hilarious and endearing to see everyone’s facial expressions. Over time, I’ve learned a key secret: <em>everyone</em> knows it’s cold, but the pros never scrunch up their faces. Keep cool, literally and figuratively.</p> <h3 id="the-great-aussie-towel-trick"><strong>The Great Aussie Towel Trick</strong></h3> <p>One cultural thing that really surprised me when I first moved to Australia was how casually people changed at the beach. Just a towel wrapped around the waist or chest, and somehow—like magic—they’re in dry clothes a minute later. Coming from an Asian background, this was wild to me. I’d shiver my way to the changing rooms rather than attempt this mysterious public towel dance.</p> <p>But after a few years of observation and trial-and-error, I cracked the code. There’s no secret technique. The real barrier is in your head. All you need is a <strong>big towel</strong> and the belief that you <em>won’t</em> accidentally drop it. That’s it. Confidence is key!</p> <h3 id="my-favourite-rock-pools-at-coogee"><strong>My Favourite Rock Pools at Coogee</strong></h3> <p>I’m not a fan of being pounded by waves, so I usually skip the open ocean and stick to Coogee’s rock pools. There are three that I’ve tried, each with their own vibe:</p> <ul> <li><strong>The Ross Jones Rockpool</strong> – This is my go-to when I want a quick solo swim. It’s sheltered, easy to get in and out of, and did I mention it’s free? Perfect for an impromptu ocean therapy session.</li> <li><strong>The McIver’s Ladies Baths</strong> – When I’m out with my girlfriends, this is the one we pick. It’s women-only, tucked into the cliffside, and has a peaceful vibe. Bonus: there’s a hot shower. After a winter swim, that feels like a five-star luxury.</li> <li><strong>Wylie’s Baths</strong> – This one’s a little more polished, with proper facilities, a working space, and even a café. Getting out of the cold water and into a hot coffee or chocolate? Absolute bliss.</li> </ul> <h3 id="final-tips"><strong>Final Tips</strong></h3> <ul> <li><strong>Check the conditions first</strong> – <a href="https://wylies.com.au">Wylie’s Baths</a> has a live cam you can check before heading out. The three rock pools have different levels of exposure to waves: Wylie’s gets hit the hardest, followed by the Ladies Baths, while the Ross Jones Rockpool is the most sheltered. Even when Wylie’s is closed due to rough seas, the Ross Jones Rockpool is usually calm enough.</li> <li><strong>Post-swim treats</strong> – You’ve earned it! Grab a <em>Yo-Chi</em> like a true local (frozen yogurt + toppings = happiness), hit a nearby café for something hot, or wander into one of the many restaurants or pubs around. Coogee’s full of options.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[my favourite winter ritual]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Casual work as a PhD student</title><link href="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/casual-job/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Casual work as a PhD student"/><published>2025-05-01T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-01T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/casual-job</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yongxinlyu.github.io/blog/2025/casual-job/"><![CDATA[<p>PhDs aren’t known for being well-paid. If you’re reading this, you probably know that already.</p> <p>As an international PhD student at UNSW, I managed to get by financially for most of my candidature. My husband and I both had scholarships, and with some careful budgeting and split rent, we were okay. I was never swimming in money, but I could focus on my research without worrying too much about bills.</p> <p>So, for most of my PhD, I didn’t look for casual work. I told myself it wasn’t worth it — that I wanted to give my research my full attention, and that working side gigs wouldn’t add much to my CV anyway. I thought I was being strategic. In hindsight, I was being short-sighted.</p> <p>Because once I submitted my thesis, reality hit. Hard.</p> <p>No scholarship. No income. Still on a student visa, so no full-time work. Suddenly, all those casual jobs I’d ignored started to look a lot more appealing — and necessary.</p> <p>This post is for the PhD students who haven’t submitted yet. The ones still in the middle of it, maybe thinking the same things I did. I want to tell you what I learned too late — and what I wish I’d done differently.</p> <h3 id="casual-work-more-than-a-side-hustle">Casual Work: More Than a Side Hustle</h3> <p>Let’s start with the obvious: casual work helps pay the bills. But more importantly, it does something else — it keeps you engaged, gives you structure, and opens up networks you won’t find sitting alone in your office staring at your data.</p> <p>Over the past few months, I’ve explored the casual job landscape at UNSW. Here’s what I found. Some of these gigs I took. Others, I wish I had.</p> <h3 id="1-teaching-highly-recommended">1. Teaching (Highly Recommended!)</h3> <p>My top recommendation is to look into teaching-related roles. These include:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Lab demonstrations</strong></li> <li><strong>Tutoring</strong></li> <li><strong>Teaching assistant roles</strong></li> <li><strong>Marking assignments or exams</strong></li> </ul> <p>Let me be blunt: if you want a future in academia in Australia, you need teaching experience. Full stop.</p> <p>I was told this many times during my PhD, but I brushed it off. My school didn’t offer courses directly tied to my research, and I wasn’t particularly interested in wrangling a room full of undergrads. I was busy, research was demanding, and teaching felt like a distraction.</p> <p>But here’s what I didn’t realise: you don’t have to teach your topic. You just need to teach. UNSW is a big place. There are plenty of courses across faculties that welcome PhD students as tutors, demonstrators, and markers. You just have to ask.</p> <p>Reach out to lecturers. Email course convenors. Most will be happy to hear from someone enthusiastic and reliable. Even if they don’t have openings immediately, they’ll remember your name next time.</p> <p><strong>Tip:</strong> Teaching roles follow the academic calendar. If you want a spot in Term 2, start asking in Term 1.</p> <h4 id="nervous-about-teaching">Nervous about teaching?</h4> <p>I was too! I highly recommend training programs like UNSW’s <a href="https://www.teaching.unsw.edu.au/beginning-teach-ecrs-and-hdrs">Beginning to Teach</a>. It was low-stakes, supportive, and helped me understand what goes into planning a class — the prep, the pacing, the expectations. Turns out, teaching isn’t just about speaking confidently. It’s about designing a session that works even when you’re not at your best.</p> <h3 id="2-outreach">2. Outreach</h3> <p>Another fulfilling option is participating in outreach programs. These are often aimed at high school students, the general public, or underrepresented communities.</p> <p>I volunteered with the <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/science/engage-with-us/unsw-stemm-champions-program">UNSW STEMM Champions Program</a> and participated in events like:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://pintofscience.com.au"><strong>Pint of Science</strong></a> – where I gave a talk about my research in a pub!</li> <li><strong>Science in the Swamp</strong></li> <li><strong>STEMM Champions blog</strong> (here’s a <a href="https://blogs.unsw.edu.au/stemmchampions/blog/2023/06/">link to my post</a>!)</li> </ul> <p>Friends of mine have been involved in <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/science/study-with-us/scix-school-extension-program"><strong>SciX</strong></a>, <strong>Open Day</strong>, and other public-facing events.</p> <p>Some of these gigs were voluntary. Some were paid. All were worthwhile.</p> <p>You learn to talk about your research in plain English. You meet people outside your field. And you start to remember that science isn’t just something we do in isolation — it’s something we share.</p> <h3 id="3-exam-supervision">3. Exam Supervision</h3> <p>Here’s one I hadn’t thought of until recently: exam supervision.</p> <p>My friend Mariana told me about it. I was curious — I’d never taken an exam at UNSW, so I wanted to see how it all worked. Turns out, exams here are supervised by a separate team, not the teaching staff. And most of them are online — which is wild if you’re used to paper exams and proctors walking around with clipboards.</p> <p>I only did two shifts. It was chaotic at first — you’re thrown in and expected to learn fast. But it was fascinating. I even ended up supervising a computer science exam on machine learning, which I love, and had a great chat with one of the students.</p> <h3 id="some-final-thoughts">Some Final Thoughts</h3> <p>Here’s the thing: I thought ignoring casual jobs was helping me focus. In reality, I was isolating myself.</p> <p>Teaching, outreach, even admin jobs — they connect you to the university in ways that research alone doesn’t. They give you experience you can actually use. And, crucially, they remind you that you have skills beyond your thesis.</p> <p>I’m not saying everyone should take on loads of extra work. Burnout is real. But a few hours a week of something different? It might be just what you need.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[balancing research and rent]]></summary></entry></feed>